So another problem that comes across a lot of developers as they're growing as a
view developer is, at some point, they need to access a child-components data or
methods from the parent.
And now this might sound a little odd because most of us are, well, let's face it,
the standard data flow model where you see it's top down, right?
Parent pass is up to the child, child does stuff with it, and then if anything
we have an event that like, we emit something that comes up, just like standard web
model, and then again, it just flows down.
However, there are times where you're just simply not going to have the ability to do so.
It might be because you're using a third party library, or maybe your library author
where you don't know what context your component is going to be ingested in.
These are great candidates for this concept known as scope slots.
On the podcast episode we did for fundamentals, we were talking about like one of the most
commonly like confused concepts of you.
And I would say that in my teaching experience, scope slots tends to be the one that a lot
of people don't quite grasp because I think it's
kind of unintuitive, and then, but hopefully we're going to go over this, it'll make
more sense to people, and they'll feel more comfortable using it in their component design
as they see, as they see fit.
OK, so let's go ahead and what we're going to do, we're going to create a, let's do
a slot demo.view, and then call it slot demo, and then we'll make sure
it renders on our sandbox page.
This time I'm actually going to delete some of this stuff so that we are slot demo perfect.
Great, flip, flip, flip, all right.
So going back to our sandbox page, all right, we have a slot demo component is rendering.
Great.
OK, so here's the kind of problem that ends up happening, is that in the event we have
some, OK, so let's go ahead and actually let me sled up my slot demo here, and we're
going to go ahead and we're going to do a main, and we're going to do three different blocks.
OK, we're going to have a slot for the header, we're going to have a default, so let's see,
let's see, oh, slot demo title.
So this is how you set like default content, in case no one sets it up, then you have your
default slot, which is where everything else will go, and then I'm going to do one more
name slot called the footer, and then like this is the bottom.
OK, so now that we have this, the way we have our sandbox page, actually let me close
some of these, so we actually clean up the file up here a bit, so it's easier for everyone.
OK, don't see it that.
OK, so the way this would work is, right, when the typical slot component, you would have
a template that would then have the V slot pass with the name, so in this case, let's
say, actually we don't need header actually right now because that has demo content,
so let's just call this and say, here is my normal body content, and then we'll also
have a template for the footer, this is my footer content, and so if we save this and
look over here, you'll see here, do do do do, slot demo title is here, and then up, we might
have noticed that footer content and the main content is not showing up, do do, oh, it's
because of this, there we go, OK, sorry, what we saw here, actually I should demo that,
is that when you have a template here without basically designating what slot it is, as you
can see here, it doesn't actually know where to go, and so if you wanted to wrap it in
a template block, you can basically, it's called default, it means it's rapid like this,
and we can see here, we still have all three.
Now if we can envision a slot demo has some data that we want to get access to, right?
So let's just use the simple counter example in this particular case, and so it's keeping
track of the current count, and we'll just make it at a rough of 10.
And so typically you would think, OK, well, again, this is a component, I want to render
my thing, so I'm going to say, well, current count is this.
And so now if I go ahead and take out the default slot, we'll see here, as you would expect,
current count is 10, right?
That makes sense.
The content of the scope slots is what happens when you need the parent to actually kind
of rearrange the, like, kind of get access to the data so that it can rearrange the way it
actually wants it to be displayed.
So in this case, let's say the parent is unable to reach into the child to say, actually
what I wanted to say is current count is even, right?
So what you would need to do in this case is you would actually need to scope slots is this
concept of basically passing data into a slot as a prop that then surfaces to the parent.
So think of it as a backward slot, and this is one of the reasons why it's kind of weird.
So what do I mean by that?
So what demo this real quick?
We have our default slot here, right?
And what we're going to do is we're going to say, okay, we're passing the count.
This is like defining any other prop for any other component.
We're defining a prop called count, although to be clear, there's no defined props up here.
This is clearly just on the slot.
And we're passing it the value of current count, although I need to bind this, okay?
So all we've done is give a prop to a slot.
That's all we've done so far.
Now what we're going to do is inside, I'll be explicit with this one, so that's easy
to see.
Is that you're going to be able to access your slot props through this, basically, by accessing
the value.
So I usually like to demo it like this, so you get access to the slot props object,
which you can already see, has the property count on it, waiting for you.
So now I can be like, this is my cool slot props.count.
Can you see here?
Now the parent is the one controlling how the data from the child is being rendered.
Again, you might be thinking, okay, when would I normally use this?
And the fact is, you normally wouldn't, right?
This is part of the whole intermediate view thing, right?
This is a common example, let's say you're designing a select input, right?
As we know select drop downs, they have a lot of different
stylings that can be used in a lot of different scenarios.
So you might want to create like a generic select drop down,
that provides all the options, all the data in needs,
but the context in which it's being used, right?
Maybe in one select drop down, you have a picture being rendered on the left-hand side with some
text and it has different styles.
This, the scope slots or what I like to call slot props,
allow you to basically have a generic component that then someone ingest and then can control
like how things are being displayed.
Again, so typically used for third party libraries,
a perfect example of this is view multi-select, this one, there we go.
So we can see here, right?
This is the example of a drop down where you have the license on the left,
but then you have images and stuff on the right.
But then if we take a look at some of the other custom option templates,
I mean, you can see here, in this case, they want the image on the left,
they want the text on the right.
And so what you'll see here is they're actually exposing the template, right?
And they're saying, oh, here are the props.
And then just display normal HTML as you want, right?
The props have already been defined, take the image, take the labels,
style it, however you see fit.
And because, right, because if you're the author of this library for multi-select,
you have no, like, first of all, whoever's using it,
cannot just reach into your component to do it.
You're providing a generic functionality, which is to be able to provide things,
like multiple tagging, searching, like, you're providing generic logic
and functionality for the component.
Styling and stuff, that's up to how they ingest it.